Finding Aid for Kenneth Richard Gibson papers, 1930-1956
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kenneth Richard Gibson papers 1930-1956
Gibson, Kenneth Richard, 1895-1959.
1 oversize folders
14 linear feet
851322 Aa 2; UAm
Detroit, Michigan, dentist and leader in public health dentistry; director of the Dental Division of the Children's Fund of Michigan (1929-1948), director of the Child Health division of the Children's Fund (1948-1954), and administrator of the Northern and Central Michigan Children’s Clinics. Correspondence, reports, budgets, questionnaires, inventories, and form books concerning dental programs of the Children’s Fund; lectures and articles on dental practice and education; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Kenneth Gibson (donor no. 4068 ) and came to the library in August 1963.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Kenneth Richard Gibson was born December 12, 1895, in Dunbar, Wisconsin. He graduated from the University of Michigan School of Dentistry in 1918, and earned his master's degree in public health in 1938. Between 1943 and 1946, he pursued additional graduate coursework at the School of Public Health. In 1921, he was appointed director of the Bureau of Dentistry and Oral Hygiene of the Michigan Department of Health. He served for three years until 1924, when he returned to private practice.
In 1929, Gibson was named director of the Dental Division of the Children's Fund of Michigan, a charitable fund established by Senator James Couzens for the care of indigent children in the state. Gibson served in this capacity until 1948. From 1948 to 1954, Gibson served as the director of the Child Health Division of the Fund. In addition, Gibson was administrator of the Northern Michigan Children's Clinic at Marquette and the Central Michigan Children's Clinic at Traverse City, and oversaw the Fund's eye program from 1948 until the mid 1950s.
Gibson served as director of the Michigan Association of Public Health, Dentists and Dental Hygienists, president of the School Health Association, president of the Michigan Public Health Association, and president of the Michigan State Society for the Promotion of Children's Dentistry. He died December 15, 1959.
The Kenneth Richard Gibson papers document his work as director of the Dental Division of the Children's Fund of Michigan and director of the Child Health Division of the Fund; his work with a number of public health and dental health professional associations; and to a lesser extent, his coursework in public health. The papers are arranged into four series: Personal, Professional Associations, Children's Fund of Michigan, Dental Division, and Children's Fund of Michigan, Child Health Division.
Subjects:
Children--Health and hygiene--Michigan.; Children's Fund of Michigan.; Dentistry--Michigan.; Dentistry--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Dentists--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.); Michigan School Health Association.; Pedodontics--Michigan.; Public health--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Children's Fund of Michigan.; Dentistry--Michigan.; Gibson, Kenneth Richard, 1895-1959.; Public health--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan--Bay County.; University of Michigan. College of Dental Surgery. Class of 1918.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal 1934-1950
  The bulk of the Personal series consists of Gibson's notes, essays, and bibliographies from his coursework in public health at the University of Michigan, from 1934 to 1946. The series also contains clippings about Gibson's career, and several photographs, including images of dental education presentations and displays, a 29th reunion photo of the University of Michigan Dental School class of 1918, and a picture of Dr. Gibson receiving a citation.
  - Certificates 1947-1949 (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1941-1948, undated (Box 1)
  - School papers
    - Hygiene, and public health notes 1934-1935 (Box 1)
    - Notes and syllabi 1935-1938, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Exams and notes 1937 (Box 1)
    - Bibliographic notes 1942-1944 (Box 1)
    - Essays on public health and health sector labor market 1943-1946 (Box 1)
    - Essays and notes 1944-1946 (Box 1)
    - Notes: Public health 1944-1946 (Box 1)
    - Coursework for Public Health Ph.D. 1945-1946 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1936-1950 (Box 1)
    (includes group photo of 29th reunion of U of M Dental School class of 1918)
- Professional Associations 1941-1956
  The Professional Associations series documents Gibson's work with regional and national dental health, public health, and school health associations. Records include correspondence, minutes, and reports from the American School Health Association, the Michigan School Health Association, the Michigan Public Health Association, the Michigan Health Officers Association, the American Association of Orthodontics, and the American College of Dentists.
  - American Association of Orthodontics, Public Relations Bureau 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - American College of Dentists, Committee on Public Relations 1956 (Box 1)
  - American and Michigan School Health Associations 1946-1949, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - American and Michigan School Health Associations 1946-1949, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - American School Health Association
    - State Directors correspondence 1951 (Box 2)
    - State Membership Chairmen correspondence 1951-1952 (Box 2)
    - Committee on Dental Membership 1942-1949 (Box 2)
    - Atlantic City meeting 1941 (Box 2)
    - New York City meeting 1953 (Box 2)
  - Chicago Dental Society meeting 1942 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Department of Health, Michigan Waterworks newsletters 1950-1954 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Health Council bulletins 1949-1954 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Health Officers Association
    - State Aid Bill 1949 (Box 2)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Public Health Association
    - 1946-1947, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Conferences 1943-1953 (Box 2)
  - Michigan School Health Association 1943-1954, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Children's Fund of Michigan, Dental Division 1930-1953
  The largest series, Children's Fund of Michigan, Dental Division, documents Gibson's two decades as director of the division. Administrative records in this series include annual reports and activity summaries for the division, forms used in the administration of dental programs, and Gibson's copies of several Children's Fund and Child Health Division reports. The Dental Division series also includes Gibson's incoming and outgoing correspondence with program staff, public health officials, vendors of equipment and supplies, and fellow dental practitioners and educators. Notable in this series are program reports kept by month and by county for the regular dental program and the Summer Dental Relief Program. These reports provide detailed information about the population of children receiving services, locations of clinics, and the interactions between the program staff and local public health officials and educators. There are also reports and correspondence related to several Detroit-area dental programs operated by the division. Finally, the series contains Gibson's files on dental education and research, including articles and lectures on dental practice and post-graduate education; and papers of several sections of the division's Dental Study Club.
  - Administrative
    - CFM annual reports 1931-1948 (Box 3)
    - Children's Fund and Dental Program reports 1930-1944 (Box 3)
    - Annual reports and budgets 1931-1949, 12 folders (Box 3)
    - Budgets, Dental Division 1946-1948 (Box 3)
    - Form books, series 2-10, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Form books, series 11-25, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and topical files
    - Regular dental program correspondence 1930-1940, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and reports 1930-1946, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Inter-office memos 1934-1948 (Box 4)
    - Thank you letters 1931-1941 (Box 4)
    - American Dental Association Survey of Dental Programs in Schools questionnaires 1943-1944 (Box 4)
    - Children's Fund of Michigan Dental Advisory Committee 1936 (Box 4)
    - County Dental Advisory Committee lists 1934-1936 (Box 4)
    - Future Dental Programs 1953 (Box 4)
    - Inventory of regular dental equipment and supplies 1949-1953 (Box 4)
    - Junior and senior high school examinations 1942 (Box 4)
    - Marquette Dental Meeting 1938-1939, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Michigan State Dental Society Legislative Committee 1940-1941 (Box 4)
    - Michigan State Board of Dentistry correspondence 1941-1947 (Box 4)
    - Michigan House Enrolled Act 79 (regulation of dentistry) 1945 (Box 4)
    - Northwest High School data 1940-1948 (Box 4)
    - Practicing dentists in certain Michigan counties 1942-1943 (Box 5)
    - Prices of standard equipment and supplies 1935-1951 (Box 5)
    - Regular dental staff 1930-1951, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Reports and program histories 1934-1951 (Box 5)
      (received from Dr. Kenneth A. Easlick, Division of Dentistry, MI Department of Health)
    - Requests for dental service 1935-1949 (Box 5)
    - Special reports 1931 (Box 5)
    - War Manpower Commission 1943-1947 (Box 5)
  - Programs
    - Regular dental program, Dr. Ketcik correspondence 1930-1944, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Regular dental program, correspondence and reports 1948-1950 (Box 5)
    - Monthly reports 1932-1949, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Field trip reports 1934-1944, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - County reports, questionnaires, etc. 1930s-1940s
      - Alger, Schoolcraft, Baraga, and Iron Counties (Box 5)
    - County reports, questionnaires, etc. 1930s-1940s
      - Bay County (Box 6)
      - Berrien, Branch, Grand Traverse, Huron Counties and Lincoln, Monroe, and Wyandotte (Box 6)
      - Cheboygan, Alpena, Presque Isle, and Montmorency Counties (Box 6)
      - Chippewa and Delta Counties (Box 6)
      - Clare, Gladwin, and Arenac Counties (Box 6)
      - Crawford, Roscommon, Missaukee, and Kalkaska Counties (Box 6)
      - Dickinson County and Hamtramck (Box 6)
      - Emmet, Otsego, Antrim, and Charlevoix Counties (Box 6)
      - Houghton, Luce, and Mackinac Counties (Box 6)
      - Macomb County (Box 6)
      - Mason, Manistee, Wexford, and Sanilac Counties (Box 6)
      - Mecosta, Osceola, Wexford, and Menominee Counties (Box 6)
      - Newaygo, Lake, and Oceana Counties (Box 6)
      - North and South Oakland County (Box 7)
      - Ogemaw, Oscoda, Alcona, Iosco Counties and Boys Club of Detroit (Box 7)
      - Ontonagon and Baraga Counties (Box 7)
      - Ottawa County (Box 7)
      - Saginaw County (Box 7)
      - Rural Wayne County (Box 7)
    - Summer Dental Relief Program
      - Applications for employment 1935-1951 (10% selection retained) (Box 7)
      - Reports and clinic locations 1930-1932 (Box 7)
      - Reports 1933 (Box 7)
      - Correspondence, reports, and clinic locations 1934-1936, 4 folders (Box 7)
      - Manual of procedure 1936 (Box 7)
      - Correspondence, reports, and clinic locations 1937-1939, 5 folders (Box 8)
      - Manual of procedure 1940 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, reports, and clinic locations 1940-1942, 6 folders (Box 8)
    - Summer Dental Sodium Fluoride Program, correspondence by clinic location 1949 (Box 8)
    - Summer Dental Sodium Fluoride Program
      - Correspondence by clinic location 1949-1951, 7 folders (Box 9)
      - Location assignments and program summary 1952 (Box 9)
    - Regular Dental Health Education Program 1937-1938 (Box 9)
    - Boy's Club of Detroit Dental Program 1932-1949, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Detroit Dental Program 1936-1939, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Detroit Dental Program inspection 1936-1937, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Detroit Dental Society, Physical Fitness Dental Program 1943-1948 (Box 10)
    - Detroit Emergency Dental Program 1934 (Box 10)
    - Detroit School Dental Program and Detroit Post-Graduate Course 1935-1936 (Box 10)
    - High School Victory Corps Dental Program 1943 (Box 10)
    - National Youth Administration Dental Program 1941, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - WPA Dental Program (proposed) 1939 (Box 10)
  - Dental Education and Research
    - American Society of Dentistry for Children, Academy Committee correspondence 1942 (Box 10)
    - Caries control workshop 1947 (Box 10)
    - Child Health Institute exhibit 1937 (Box 10)
    - Children's Fund of Michigan Dental Program articles and lectures 1932-1945 (Box 10)
    - Children's Fund of Michigan Dental Staff lectures and educational material 1936-1940 (Box 10)
    - Child Health Association address 1939 (Box 10)
    - Council on Dental Education registers and articles 1940-1944 (Box 10)
    - Dental Study Club
      - Reports 1938-1946 (Box 11)
      - Anesthesia Section articles and lectures 1935-1940 (Box 11)
      - Health Education Section articles, lectures, and pamphlets 1938-1948 (Box 11)
      - Operative Division articles and lectures 1938-1947 (Box 11)
      - Oral Surgery Section articles and lectures 1938-1940 (Box 11)
    - Dr. Bion R. East, dental caries correspondence and articles 1939-1943 (Box 11)
    - Forsyth Dental Infirmary, Boston 1935 (Box 11)
    - Kenneth Gibson dental health and education lectures, articles, and reprints 1937-1944 (Box 11)
    - Lantern slide lists 1939 (Box 11)
    - Loan and internship plan for dental students circa 1938 (Box 11)
    - Lost permanent tooth index for evaluating dental programs 1937-1939 (Box 11)
    - Material for dental manual undated (Box 11)
    - Michigan Department of Health education material 1943 (Box 11)
    - Michigan State Dental Society/Detroit District Dental Society
      - Articles and lectures 1935-1937 (Box 11)
      - Joint Committee on Public Health and Education 1937-1938 (Box 11)
    - Post-graduate courses at Ann Arbor 1937 (Box 11)
    - Proposed orthodontia program data and clinical research project in orthodontia 1935-1936 (Box 11)
    - University of Michigan lectures and educational material 1930-1942 (Box 11)
    - University of Michigan School of Public Health, Institute of Dental Health Economics 1944 (Box 11)
    - X-Ray and Root Canal Clinic 1935-1937 (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous lectures and educational material 1935-1950, 3 folders (Box 12)
- Children's Fund of Michigan, Child Health Division 1930-1954
  The Children's Fund of Michigan, Child Health Division series includes annual reports and activity summaries, monthly reports, budgets and financial statements, records of the Fund's eye program, and reports and correspondence related to the Central and Northern Michigan Children's Clinics. This series documents Gibson's years as director of the Child Health Division, but it also includes earlier reports, financial information, and a small amount of the correspondence of his predecessor, Dr. Bernard W. Carey.
  - Budgets and financial statements 1930-1942, 1948-1952, 8 folders (Box 12)
  - Annual reports 1942-1954 (Box 13)
  - Annual activities summaries 1931-1943 (Box 13)
  - Monthly reports 1939-1946, 7 folders (Box 13)
  - Monthly reports 1946-1947 (Box 14)
  - Dr. Carey's memos, reports, and bulletins 1943-1945 (Box 14)
  - Eye Program monthly records 1948-1953 (Box 14)
  - Eye program correspondence and reports 1948-1954 (Box 14)
  - Central Michigan Children's Clinic annual reports 1940-1942 (Box 14)
  - Central and Northern Michigan Children's Clinics monthly reports 1947-1949, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Northern Michigan Children's Clinic correspondence 1948-1951 (Box 14)
Related Material
The researcher should also consult the Children's Fund of Michigan records available at the Bentley Historical Library and the papers of others associated with the Fund, especially Icie Gertrude Macy Hoobler and William J. Norton.